A Guide to the Records of the Citizen's Committee for School Improvement, 1946-1969
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Records of the Citizen's Committee for School Improvement, 1946-1969
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 9
2 boxes.
Citizen's Committee for School Improvement
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Record Group 9 is mostly composed of materials from two donations from B. Alden Lillywhite and Barnard Joy, respectively. This guide was made possible by grants from the National Historical Publications and Records Commission and the Washington Forrest Foundation.
Historical Information
The Citizen's Committee for School Improvement (CCSI), a nonpartisan association, was formed in Arlington, Virginia in 1946, with the immediate purpose of influencing the selection of Arlington School Board candidates. The Committee's constitution, adopted in 1947, states that the organization's goals "are to advance the nature of the population, the needs of the time, and the resources of the community." During the year of the organization's founding, CCSI was also involved in the establishment of kindergartens in Arlington County. The first chairman was Oscar R. LeBeau (1946-1947), followed by B. Alden Lillywhite (1947-1949) and Reed K. Pond (1949-1950). Later chairmen included Robert E. Reynolds and Charles B. Wood.
The Maryland-Virginia Citizen's Committee for the Public Schools was founded in 1950 with the purpose of bringing together leaders interested in public education from civic, business and educational organizations. Membership between the M-V CCPS and the CCSI was overlapping, and Reed K. Pond was the president of both groups in 1950. Included are membership lists, minutes and reports.
Scope and Content
Record Group 9 houses the scattered records of the Citizen's Committee for School Improvement for the period from 1946-1954 and 1956-1969 and measures 1 linear foot. The collection houses the committee's constitution, by-laws, minutes, correspondence files, resolutions, membership lists, position statements, press releases, announcements, newsletters, radio scripts, photographs and clippings. The Committee's interests in the selection of School Board candidates, the school lunch program, the improvement of teacher salaries, local bond issues, and the establishment of public kindergartens are covered in this group.
The record group also includes a few scattered records, 1950-1954, of the Maryland-Virginia Citizen's Committee for the Public Schools. Included are membership lists, minutes and reports.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged into series according to either primary functions of the committees and/or type of material. Within each series, folders are in chronological order, and documents within folders are in rough chronological order. Undated items are placed at the front of the folder.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
RG 7, Arlington County Public Schools
Related Material
RG 70, Barnard Joy Papers
Index Terms
Subjects:
Arlington Public Schools (Arlington, Va.); Public schools -- United States.; Education -- Aims and objectives -- Virginia; Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Citizen's Committee for School Improvement Records
  - Constitution and Bylaws 1946, 1948, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Regular Meeting Minutes 1949-1950, 1959-1969 (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes 1949-1950, 1955-1969 (Box 1)
  - Resolutions 1946-1962 (Box 1)
  - Membership Lists 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - Membership Lists 1957-1960 (Box 1)
  - Membership Lists 1961-1967 (Box 1)
  - Chairman Oscar LeBeau 1951, 1954, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Chairman Robert Reynolds, n.d. (Box 1)
  - CCSI Newsletters 1946-1948, 1950-1967 (intermittent) (Box 1)
  - Position Statements and Reports to School Board 1951, 1956-1967 (Box 1)
  - Announcements and Miscellaneous Statements 1946-1967 (Box 1)
  - Founding Statement 1946 (Box 1)
  - Statements Regarding Kindergartens 1946 (Box 1)
  - Press Releases, n.d. (Box 1)
  - CCSI Radio Scripts 1946-1947 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous CCSI Reports 1951, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Chairman and Vice Chairman Correspondence 1941, 1946-1947, 1951, 1952, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Chairman and Vice Chairman Correspondence 1957-1965 (Box 2)
- Other Education Initiatives and Groups
  - Arlington School Board Nominating Conference Minutes 1947, 1953, n.d. (Box 2)
  - Arlington School Board Nominating Conference Candidate Information 1947-1959 (Box 2)
  - School Board Budgets 1946-1961 (Box 2)
  - Arlington Education Association Literature 1964, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Literature of Other Education Assocations 1945-1965 (Box 2)
  - School Lunch Program 1947 (Box 2)
  - Education Legistlation 1947, 1951, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1946-1951 (Box 2)
  - James Monroe Elementary Handbook and Doctrine Newsletter 1950-1954 (intermittent) (Box 2)
- Maryland-Virginia Citizen's Committee for the Public Schools (M-V CCPS)
  - Policies and Procedures 1950 (Box 2)
  - Membership Lists 1950-1954 (Box 2)
  - Minutes 1950-1954 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence 1950-1954 (Box 2)
  - Report on Anne Arundel County 1954 (Box 2)